Merritt, Walter Gordon Papers 5344
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Walter Gordon Merritt Papers
1906-1953
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Merritt, Walter Gordon
5344
1.5 cubic feet
1.5 linear ft.
Papers, articles, case files.
Papers of attorney Walter Gordon Merritt documenting his legal work for management interests. Merritt's papers contain legal briefs and transcripts, arranged alphabetically by plaintiff name.
2298500
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, April 09, 2014
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 11, 2019
Biographical / Historical
Labor lawyer and author. Walter Gordon Merritt (1880-1968) was the son of a Danbury, Ct. hatshop owner. He graduated from Harvard and went to New York Law School, afterwards becoming a partner in the law firm of Windels, Merritt & Ingrahamat. Merritt had a successful career as a labor lawyer representing management; his most famous case was "Dietrich E. Lowe and Martin Fuchs vs. Martin Lawler, et al.," popularly known as the "Danbury Hatters Case." He also authored a number of articles on issues of labor relations. As might be expected, they are largely written from the management perspective.
Scope and Contents
Consist of documents relating to court cases in which Merritt represented management and reprints of articles written by Merritt. Include legal documents (briefs, transcripts, petitions, and decisions) relating to cases brought before the Superior Court of Fairfax County, the United States District Court (Connecticut), United States Circuit Courts of Appeals (Connecticut, Arkansas, and New York), the State Supreme Court of New York, and the Supreme Court of the United States. These cases include: "Dietrich E. Loewe and Martin Fuchs vs. Martin Lawler et al." ("Danbury Hatters Case") (1906-1908); "The Lundoff-Bucknell Company vs. Charles B. Smith" (1911); "D.E. Loewe vs. The Savings Bank of Danbury" (n.d); "The Auburn Draying Company vs. William Wardell" (1913); "Louis Boussert and John Boussert vs. Frederick Dhuy, etc. et al." (1911-1912); "Abro J. Newton Company vs. Henry Erickson, William O'Grady, Frederick Dhuy, Harry Lea, individually and as Business Agents of the Joint District Council, etc." (1912); "Charles H. Finley, Receivor of Coronado Coal Company vs. United Mine Workers of America" (1920-1925); "Duplex Printing Press Company vs. Emil Deering" (1917); and "Hat Corporation of America vs. United Hatters, Cap and Millinery Workers Union et al." (second Danbury Hatters case) (1953). Reprints of articles and pamphlets by Merritt include his reflections on the open and closed shop, industrial liberty, social control, industrial welfare, cooperation between management and labor, factory solidarity as opposed to class solidarity, and labor legislation (1912-1923).
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Danbury Hatters Case, 1910.; Labor-management cooperation. United States.; Deering, Emil; Erickson, Henry; Fuchs, Martin; Lawler, Martin; Lowe, Dietrich E.; Merritt, Walter Gordon; Smith, Charles B.; Abro J. Newton Company.; Coronado Coal Company; Duplex Printing Press Company; Hat Corporation of America; Lundoff-Bucknell Company; United Hat, Cap and Millinery Workers.; United Hatters, Cap and Millinery Workers' International Union
2298500
- Consist of documents relating to court cases in which Merritt represented management and reprints of articles written by Merritt. Include legal documents (briefs, transcripts, petitions, and decisions) relating to cases brought before the Superior Court o (Box 1)
  - Albro J. Newton Co. v. Henry Erickson, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Auburn Draying Co. v. William Wardell, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Duplex Printing Press v. Emil J. Deering, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Finley v. United Mine Workers, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Hat Corporation of America v. United Hatters, Cap, and Millinery Workers International Union, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lawlor v. Loewe (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lawlor v. Loewe transcript, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Scope and Contents
    Volume 1
  - Lawlor v. Loewe transcript, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Volume 2
  - Lawlor v. Loewe transcript, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Volume 3
  - Lawlor v. Loewe transcript, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Volume 4
  - Lawlor v. Loewe transcript, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Volume 5
- Loewe v. Savings Bank of Danbury, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Louis Bossert and Son v. Frederick Dhuy, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Lundoff-Bicknell Co. v. Charles Smith, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Wilson and Adams Co. v. Patrick D. Pearce (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Pamphlets (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Includes: Loewe Case or Danbury Hatters' Case, The Closed Shop, Domestic Free Trade and Organized Labor, Factory Solidarity or Class Solidarity, The Open Shop and Industrial Liberty, The Four C's of Industry, Social Control of Industrial Warfare, Labor Le